Finding Aid for Alumnae Council(University of Michigan) records, 1890-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alumnae Council (University of Michigan) records 1890-1991 1917-1980
University of Michigan. Alumnae Council.
4.5 linear ft.
9245 Bimu H1 2
The University of Michigan Alumnae Council was founded in 1917 as a group to support women at the University of Michigan. They are active fund-raisers, and use the money to sponsor women’s housing, scholarships, and organizations at the University. The records consist of photographs and meeting minutes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The photographs were donated in several accessions by the Alumnae Council 60th Anniversary Committee and came to the library in 1976-1977. The minutes were accessioned in 2002 from the Alumnae Council and the Alumni Association (Donor # 6001 and 1617 ).
The record group is open without restriction.
The University of Michigan Alumnae Council was founded in 1917, and its constitution adopted in June 1924. The group was established as a branch of the general Alumni Association, to support the interests of women at the University of Michigan. The Alumnae Council has since come to be an equal organization with the Alumni Association. They raise funds, which they use to support women’s housing, such as the Alumnae House and Henderson House, for fellowships and scholarships, and donate to University groups. They also encourage women to enter college, and help them once they arrive at the university.
Their earliest projects focused on the construction of buildings where women could gather. They were instrumental in raising funds for the construction of the Michigan League in 1921, and sports facilities for women. They also funded the construction of women’s housing, and were great supporters of establishing women athletic programs.
The Alumnae Council remains active, raising funds for scholarships, and donating money annually to a university project. The Council continues to promote the interests of women, as well as promoting the university to the community.
The website (as of January 2005) is available at the following URL: http://umclubs.com/alumnae/
The records of the University of Michigan Alumnae Council are divided into two series: Photographs and Meeting Minutes.
Subjects:
Alpha Tau Omega. Beta Lambda Chapter (University of Michigan); Alumnae House (University of Michigan); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Aerial photographs.; Betsey Barbour House (University of Michigan); Canoes.; Collegiate Sorosis (University of Michigan); Henderson House (University of Michigan); Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Iron and Steel Club (University of Michigan); Kappa Alpha Theta. Eta Chapter (University of Michigan); Lodeesen's Orchestra.; Martha Cook Building (University of Michigan); Music ensembles.; Sleds and sleighs.; University of Michigan--Commencements.; University of Michigan. Girls Glee Club.; University of Michigan. Junior Girls Play.; University of Michigan. Junior Hop--1912.; Mud Bowl, Ann Arbor, Mich.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; University of Michigan. Women's League.
Contributors:
Carr, Lauren Duane.; Meyer, Suzanne M.; Sargeant, Ellen Maude.; Smith, Grace.
Genre Terms:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.
- Photographs, ca. 1890-1980, 0.5 linear feet
  Photographs (0.5 linear feet, ca. 1890-1980) predominantly depict female students at the university. There are also photographs of women athletes in action, and of the interior of the Michigan League. Many of the photographs were collected as part of the organization’s efforts to celebrate their 60th anniversary.
  - Alumnae Council activities
    - Alumni Leadership Conference, October 1972 (Box 1)
    - Groups (Box 1)
    - Individuals (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Myers, Alison Tennant (Box 1)
    - 100th Anniversary of the admission of women to the University of Michigan fashion show, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Operation Friendship (Box 1)
    - Registration (for fashion show, 1970?) (Box 1)
  - Photographs collected by the 60th Anniversary Committee
    - Alumnae House, ca. 1917 (Box 1)
    - Carr, Lauren D. Photos include Iron and Steel Club and student room, 1894 with musicians (Box 1)
    - Collegiate Sorosis. Photos include Mud Bowl (Box 1)
    - Commencement, 1912 (Box 1)
    - Football fans in stands, 1925 and 1920s undated (Box 1)
    - Junior Hop Album, 1912. (Box 1)
      (Photos include Alpha Tau Omega house and groups, and sleigh ride)
    - Meyer, Suzanne M. Photographs include Betsy Barbour dormitory, 1930s (Box 1)
    - Michigan League. (Box 1)
      (Photos include aerial view of campus before construction of League; also photos of rooms and of drinking fountain)
    - Miscellaneous (1) (Box 1)
      (Photos include Junior Girls Play, 1941; Lodeesen's Orchestra, 1926; Girls' Glee Club, 1920s; and Martha Cook, Henderson House, and Alpha Tau Omega groups)
    - Miscellaneous (2) (Box 1)
      Photos include Women's League Fancy Dress Party (dressed like Old Dutch Cleanser women), 1913; U-M ambulance units, 1917; 1912 Senior Sing; and fraternities and other groups
    - Sargeant, Ellen M. Photos, ca. 1912-1916 (Box 1)
      Includes Women's League, Girls' Glee Club, Junior Girls Play, Kappa Alpha Theta, student rooms, Huron River, and canoeing)
    - Smith, Grace. Photos, ca. 1900-1903 (Box 1)
      (includes student room)
    - Theatrical productions and players, ca. 1910-1930 (Box 1)
      (include Union Minstrels on carriage)
- Meeting Minutes, 1917-1977, 1989-1991, 3 linear feet
  Meeting Minutes (3 linear feet, 1917-1977) are in bound volumes, with materials arranged chronologically. In addition to the meeting minutes of the Council, the volumes also include correspondence, memos, newsletters, programs for events, and reports to the Council.
  - 1917-1957, 7 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1957-1966, 3 volumes (Box 3)
  - 1966-1977, 3 volumes (Box 4)
  - 1989-1999, 1 volume (Box 5)
- Adminitrative Records
  - Alumnae Council Governing Board Handbook, 1994 (Box 5)